{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "The chief religious role of these people was dispelling chaos, or isfet, and maintaining harmony, or ma'at. These people wore the pschent crown, representing the northern and southern portions of their kingdom. One of these people established a monotheistic religion centered on the sun disk, Aten. These rulers were believed to be human incarnations of the gods Osiris and Ra. For ten points, name these kings who ruled Ancient Egypt.",
      "answer": "Pharaoh"
    },
    {
      "question": "An ultranationalist group named for blue examples of these objects supported Chiang Kai-Shek’s New Life Movement. The Expedition of the Thousand was conducted by the Red [these objects], who followed Giuseppe Garibaldi. A 1922 March on Rome was led by Benito Mussolini and his followers, nicknamed for black [objects of this type]. For ten points, name this article of clothing whose “Brown” types were worn by the SA [[ESS-AY]].",
      "answer": [
        "Shirts [",
        "Blue Shirts",
        "Red Shirts",
        "Black Shirts",
        "Brown Shirts"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man's father formed a short-lived alliance with Murad II until he was imprisoned. This man and his brother Radu were jailed as children, though the Ottomans released him after an invasion of his homeland by John Hunyadi. The envoys of this man's childhood friend, Sultan Mehmed II, were impaled on stakes by this voivode [[VOY-vohd]]. The ruler of independent Wallachia [[woh-LEH-kyuh]] and a Romanian national hero was, for ten points, what infamous warlord who inspired a vampire created by Bram Stoker?",
      "answer": [
        "Vlad the Impaler or Vlad Tepes ]",
        "Vlad III",
        "Vlad Dracula",
        "or Vlad Drăculea"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This artist depicted a chain of the Order of the Golden Fleece adorning the neck of the title royal in Philip IV in Brown and Silver. One of this man's earlier artistic focuses was on scenes from the kitchen, as shown in his painting An Old Woman Cooking Eggs. One of this man's works shows the ladies-in-waiting of La Infanta Margherita in the court of her father. For ten points, name this Spanish Golden Age artist who created the painting Las Meninas.",
      "answer": "Diego Velázquez or Diego Rodríguez de Silva y Velázquez 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 1"
    },
    {
      "question": "Edward R. Murrow ran an episode of See It Now that criticized this politician for his interrogation of Annie Lee Moss. This man, who ran for Senate on the slogan \"Congress needs a tail-gunner,\" was chastised by Joseph Welch with the question, “have you no sense of decency?” For ten points, name this Wisconsin senator who claimed to have a list of 205 known communists in the state department, driving the Second Red Scare.",
      "answer": "Joseph McCarthy"
    },
    {
      "question": "A holder of this position became the highest-ranking U.S. official to visit Antarctica in 2016, staying overnight at McMurdo Station. One of these people claimed the U.S. went to Afghanistan to \"deal with the folks who attacked us on 9/11 and we have succeeded in that mission\" in response to comparisons of the fall of Kabul with the capture of Saigon. Antony Blinken and John Kerry are recent Democrats to hold this office. For ten points, name this position, the primary foreign minister of the United States.",
      "answer": [
        "Secretary of State",
        "State Secretary"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Sixth century Byzantine monks established a pilgrimage site for this figure's purported burial site on Mount Nebo. While this figure was tending the sheep of his father- in-law, a bush caught fire without burning and told this man \"I am who I am.\" This Biblical figure caused a series of plagues in one country, and he parted the Red Sea in Exodus 14. For ten points, name this Biblical prophet who delivered the Israelites from Egyptian slavery.",
      "answer": [
        "Moses",
        "Moshe Rabbenu",
        "Musa"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler's armies forced the Truce of Ratisbon, which ceded Luxembourg to his country and concluded the War of the Reunions. This monarch survived the Fronde [[\"FROND\"]] Rebellion in his youth and employed the engineer Vauban [[VOH-BAHN]] to create star forts along his country's frontier. This king ordered his nobles to inhabit the massive Palace at Versailles. For ten points, name this \"Sun King\" of France, a long-lived absolutist monarch.",
      "answer": [
        "Louis XIV",
        "Louis the Great",
        "or Louis le Grand",
        "Louis, the Sun King",
        "Louis, le Roi Soleil before \"Sun King\""
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man's skillful turning maneuvers resulted in a decisive victory at Kennesaw Mountain, which Liddell Hart cited in calling this man the first \"modern general.\" While leading the Division of the Mississippi, this man's Special Field Orders No. 15 resulted in the phrase \"forty acres and a mule.\" In the wake of the Battle of Atlanta, this man's forces undertook the \"March to the Sea\" to the Confederate port of Savannah. The \"scorched earth tactic\" was utilized by, for ten points, which Union general during the Civil War?",
      "answer": "William Tecumseh Sherman 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 1"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city was governed by a constitution known as the Great Rhetra, written by Lycurgus. Children in this city ate \"black soup\" and were forced into the Agoge [[ah-GOG- geh]] training system from the age of seven. Elected officials known as Ephors governed this city, which was ruled by two kings. Ritual killings of the Helot underclass occurred in, for ten points, what militaristic ancient city state which rivaled Athens?",
      "answer": [
        "Sparta",
        "Lacedaemon",
        "or Laconike 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 1"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Earl Grey tea is named for one holder of this position, while another names the capital of the Australian state of Victoria. A Canadian, Andrew Bonar Law, held this position for 211 days between 1922 and 1923. As a result of the Brexit controversy, Theresa May resigned from this position in July 2019. For ten points, name this position, held since 2019 by Boris Johnson from 10 Downing Street, the head of the British government.",
        "answer": [
          "Prime Minister of the United Kingdom",
          "British Prime Minister",
          "Great Britain in place of \"United Kingdom\"",
          "PM in place of \"Prime Minister\"",
          "UK in place of \"United Kingdom\""
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Since 1902, the prime minister has almost exclusively been the majority leader of this body, the lower house of British Parliament, which meets at the Palace of Westminster alongside the House of Lords.",
        "answer": [
          "House of Commons",
          "The Commons",
          "formally: The Honourable the Commons of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland in Parliament assembled"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Just after this event, a similar event occurred on the urging of Benjamin Rush in Philadelphia. This event's participants attacked the Eleanor, Beaver, and Dartmouth, and it was planned at the Old South Meeting House. Conducted by Sons of Liberty dressed as Native Americans, for ten points, what was this destructive act of protest in which a shipment of the namesake product was destroyed in a Massachusetts harbor?",
        "answer": "Boston Tea Party"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Following the Boston Tea Party, this British king quoted Julius Caesar in a letter by saying \"The die is now cast.\"",
        "answer": "King George III"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Explorer Henri Mouhot [[moo-HOH]] was the first westerner to discover this site while serving as a missionary in Battambang, and he claimed it was a temple which \"rivalled Solomon's.\" This site, a representation of Mount Meru, was built by Suryavarman II [[soor- yah-VAHR-mahn the second]] under the influence of Chola advisors from the Indian subcontinent. The Khmer [[KMARE]] Empire built, for ten points, what palatial complex seen on the modern flag of Cambodia?",
        "answer": "Angkor Wat"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Angkor Wat was damaged during a firefight between Pol Pot's Khmer Rouge and an invading force from this country, which was led by the recently victorious Ho Chi Minh.",
        "answer": [
          "Vietnam",
          "Socialist Republic of Vietnam",
          "Democratic Republic of Vietnam",
          "North Vietnam"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country fought a month-long conflict with Ecuador in 1995 known as the Cenepa War. Beginning in 1996, the Japanese embassy in this country was the scene of a hostage crisis that lasted for four months. In this nation, Chilean Bernardo O'Higgins and Argentine general José de San Martín [[mar-TEEN]] crossed the Andes to help liberate this country from Spanish control. For ten points, name this South American country that was once the heartland of the Inca.",
        "answer": [
          "Peru",
          "Republic of Peru",
          "or República del Perú",
          "Piruw Ripuwlika",
          "Piruw Suyu"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Spanish conquistador conquered the Inca people of Peru in 1532 after winning the Battle of Cajamarca [[KAH-hah-MAR-kuh]].",
        "answer": "Francisco Pizarro or Francisco Pizarro González"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city was the center of the Affair of the Placards, which resulted from rising tensions between Catholics and Protestants. In 1871, over ten thousand people were massacred when a \"Commune\" in this city was brutally crushed. The wildcat strikes of May, 1968 were centered on this city's student population. In November 2015, an ISIS attack at a soccer stadium and the Bataclan Theatre led to over a hundred deaths in this city. For ten points, name this French city where Notre Dame caught fire in 2019.",
        "answer": [
          "Paris",
          "Paris Commune"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This world-famous Parisian museum was closed for six months at the beginning of the Covid-19 pandemic in France. It occupies a former palace used primarily for military activities.",
        "answer": "Louvre ] Museum or Louvre Palace"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The southern portion of this historical kingdom was ceded to the British in the Simla Accords. The warlord Ma Bufang held a future leader of this kingdom hostage until a ransom of Silver Dragon coins was paid. The Seventeen Points Agreement was negotiated between this kingdom's leader, Tenzin Gyatso, and the government of Mao Zedong. The Dalai Lama [[DAH-lee LAH-muh]] leads the government-in-exile of, for ten points, what historical kingdom currently controlled by China?",
        "answer": [
          "Kingdom of Tibet",
          "Bod ]",
          "Xīzàng"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Most Tibetans follows a regional variation of this faith which adheres to the teachings of Siddhartha Gautama.",
        "answer": [
          "Buddhism",
          "Tibetan Buddhism",
          "Tantric Buddhism",
          "Mahayana Buddhism 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 1"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of the few survivors of this battle were Susanna Dickinson and a slave named Joe, both of whom were spared by an enemy commander. That commander at this battle would later be defeated at the Battle of San Jacinto [[hah- SEEN-toe]]. The location of this battle was depicted on a stamp in 1856 to celebrate the anniversary of Texan statehood. A fortified mission was attacked in, for ten points, what battle of the Texan War of Independence that would go on to become a famous battle cry?",
        "answer": [
          "Battle of the Alamo",
          "\"Remember the Alamo\""
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Kentucky-born colonel was sent to reinforce the mission prior to the Battle of the Alamo. A large type of hunting knife bears this man's name.",
        "answer": [
          "James Bowie ]",
          "Bowie Knife"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The dead of these people were buried with maize in their mouth, while this people's Caracol site shows signs of post-mortem bloodletting. Women in this culture travelled to the pilgrimage site of the fertility goddess Ixchel [[EEKS-chehl]] on the isle of Cozumel. The underworld of Xibalba [[shee-BAHL-bah]] is traversed by this people's mythic \"Hero Twins\" in the compendium, Popul Vuh. For ten points, these myths were carved in the monumental architecture of what Mesoamerican civilization?",
        "answer": [
          "Mayan",
          "K'iche Maya",
          "Classical Mayans"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Mayans built several elaborate arenas to play what popular Mesoamerican sport that extended to the Aztecs and the Caribbeans?",
        "answer": [
          "Mesoamerican BallGame",
          "ōllamalīztli",
          "or pitz"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "D-Day",
      "prompt": "Concerning the invasion of France, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Major 20th-century war during which D-Day took place.",
          "answer": "World War Two or the Second World War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Supreme Allied commander and future U.S. president who masterminded the D-day landings.",
          "answer": "Dwight David Eisenhower"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dictator of the Soviet Union who demanded the Allies start a \"Second Front\" in Western Europe.",
          "answer": "Joseph Stalin or Iosif Vissarionovich Stalin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Region of northern France where the D-Day landings occurred.",
          "answer": "Normandy or Normandie"
        },
        {
          "question": "Deadliest beach where nearly 4,000 American soldiers lost their lives.",
          "answer": "Omaha Beach"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nazi field marshal known as the \"Desert Fox\" who manned the Atlantic Wall fortifications.",
          "answer": "Erwin Rommel or Johannes Erwin Eugen Rommel"
        },
        {
          "question": "Westernmost beach the Americans attacked, lying on the Cotentin peninsula.",
          "answer": "Utah Beach"
        },
        {
          "question": "Vegetable nickname given to defensive wooden poles used by the Germans to injure Allied paratroopers and gliders.",
          "answer": [
            "Rommel's Asparagus",
            "Holzpfähle",
            "Luftlandehindernis 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 1"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Life of Hannibal",
      "prompt": "Concerning the life of Hannibal, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "City-state which fought Rome in the Punic Wars and from which Hannibal hailed.",
          "answer": [
            "Carthage",
            "Carthago",
            "Qart Hadasht"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Peninsula called Hispania by the Romans, through which Hannibal initially invaded Italy.",
          "answer": "Iberian Peninsula"
        },
        {
          "question": "Large war animals that Hannibal led over the Alps.",
          "answer": "War Elephants"
        },
        {
          "question": "Noble family which included Hannibal's father, Hamilcar, and his younger brothers Hasdrubal and Mago.",
          "answer": [
            "Barcas",
            "Barcids",
            "Baraq"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Roman rival of Hannibal who defeated him at the Battle of Zama.",
          "answer": [
            "Scipio Africanus",
            "Publius Cornelius Scipio"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Devastating victory in which Hannibal annihilated nearly 50,000 Romans in a double envelopment.",
          "answer": "Battle of Cannae ]"
        },
        {
          "question": "Diadochi [[\"DIE\"-uh-DOH-kee]] state and enemy of Rome that Hannibal served in the later years of his life.",
          "answer": [
            "Seleucid Empire or Basileía tōn Seleukidōn",
            "Seleucids"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Battle of the Punic War in which Hannibal’s brother Hasdrubal was killed and beheaded.",
          "answer": "Battle of the Metaurus River 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 1"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Rivers",
      "prompt": "Given the clue, name the river which...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Is the largest in the world by discharge volume, and was opened to steamboat travel by Pedro II of Brazil.",
          "answer": "Amazon River or Rio Amazonas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is considered the flowing hair of the god Shiva and was involved in a 1951 water sharing dispute between India and Bangladesh.",
          "answer": [
            "Ganges River or Ganga",
            "Padma"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Is a colorfully-named river of China that was strategically flooded by rival nations during the Warring States period.",
          "answer": "Yellow River or Huáng hé"
        },
        {
          "question": "Turned black due to the ink from texts once contained in Baghdad's House of Wisdom.",
          "answer": "Tigris River or Dijlah"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was explored by Henry Morton Stanley and now names two African countries whose capitals sit across the river from each other.",
          "answer": "Congo River or Zaire River"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the site where Peter the Great determined to build his western-facing capital of St. Petersburg.",
          "answer": "Neva River"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the site of a 20th century economic miracle in Seoul, South Korea.",
          "answer": "Han River"
        },
        {
          "question": "Caused a blackout in Southern Brazil and Paraguay after transmission lines at its Itaipu Dam failed.",
          "answer": "Paraná River 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 1"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Chaturanga was an early version of this game, whose early twentieth century champions included Cuban prodigy José Raúl Capablanca. In 2013, World Champion Vishi Anand was defeated by Norwegian (20 pts)",
        "Magnus Carlsen, who claims the highest rating ever in this game. The 1972 World Championship in this game between Boris Spassky and Bobby Fischer (10 pts)",
        "was considered a \"battle\" of the Cold War. For ten points, name this \"Game of Kings\" which boomed in popularity thanks to the Netflix hit The Queen's Gambit."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Chess",
        "Indian Chess",
        "Shogi",
        "Xiangqi before \"Cuban\""
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) While this man was enrolled at West Point, he designed the M1913 Cavalry Saber and competed in the 1912 Summer Olympics. This man controversially organized Task Force (20 pts)",
        "Baum to rescue his son-in-law, John K. Waters. This general died shortly after being paralyzed in a low-speed car wreck. Infamously chastised for slapping two shell-shocked (10 pts)",
        "soldiers, for ten points, name this successful American general known as \"Old Blood and Guts.\""
      ],
      "answer": "George Smith Patton Jr."
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The polymath Pindar labelled this body the \"Inhospitable Sea\" and considered travelling in it to be an ill-omen. A \"deluge\" hypothesis involving this body of water might have inspired the story of (20 pts)",
        "Noah's Ark. A Russian victory on this body of water during the Battle of Sinope [[see-NOH-pee]] led to the British and French entering the Crimean War. The Montreux [[mon-TROO]] Convention allowed foreign vessels to pass to and from, (10 pts)",
        "for ten points, what sea which borders countries like Ukraine and Turkey?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Black Sea",
        "Chyornoye more",
        "Karadeniz"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The statue Lifting of the Veil of Ignorance at this location depicts a formerly enslaved man being shown the proper path by its founder. This site's Moton Field served as training grounds for its namesake \"Airmen\" who (20 pts)",
        "fought in the Second World War. An unethical study named for this institution left syphilis untreated in four hundred Black male sharecroppers for forty years to study its effects. George Washington (10 pts)",
        "Carver studied at, for ten points, which Alabama university once led by Booker T. Washington?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Tuskegee Institute",
        "Tuskegee University 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 1"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After the 1979 overthrow of Jean-Bédel Bokassa [[zhen-BEH-dehl boh-KAH- suh]], this man became the world's only reigning \"Emperor.\" This man was almost deposed in the Kyūjō [[KYOO-joh]] incident, (20 pts)",
        "which occurred prior to the \"Jewel Voice\" broadcast. This son of Taisho, [[\"TIE\"-shoh]] and grandson of Meiji [[MEH- jee]], became the only ruler on the Chrysanthemum (10 pts)",
        "Throne to experience a foreign occupation after his country was bombed with nuclear weapons. For ten points, name this Japanese emperor during World War Two."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Hirohito",
        "Shōwa"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The so-called \"English Achilles,\" John Talbot, led a campaign in this century which ended with the disastrous Battle of Castillon [[cah-steh-YOHN]], leading to the loss of (20 pts)",
        "Aquitaine. English longbowmen and the deployment of wooden stakes by the British proved vital at the Battle of Agincourt [[ah-jinn-KOHR]], a clash during this century. The Hundred Years' War (10 pts)",
        "ended in, for ten points, what century of the late Middle Ages?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Fifteenth Century",
        "1400s"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Periplus of the Erythraean [[eh-rith-REH-an]] Sea recounts how Rome traded for this commodity with the Chera Dynasty's merchants on the Malabar Coast. Zheng He's [[ZHEHNG HUHS]] voyage through the Indian (20 pts)",
        "Ocean led to this spice transforming from a luxury item to a common household product in Ming China. This spice was colloquially known as \"black gold\" in the early modern period by Europeans. Salt is (10 pts)",
        "historically paired with, for ten points, what spice?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Black Pepper",
        "Peppercorn"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Flights from this nation to Belarus were halted in November 2021 to stop Middle Eastern migrants from entering the EU. A 2016 coup attempt in this nation may have been manufactured by its president to purge the military of enemies. The (20 pts)",
        "Kurdish PKK party fought an asymmetrical war with this nation's government, which is led by Recep Tayyip Erdoğan [[EHR-doh-wahn]]. ISIS (10 pts)",
        "may have perpetrated the 2015 Ankara Bombings in, for ten points, what Anatolian nation?"
      ],
      "answer": "Republic of Turkey or Türkiye Cumhuriyeti 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 1"
    }
  ]
}